上一讲中我们看了一个公钥加密系统
In the previous lecture, we looked at a public key
是基于RSA构建的
encryption system that is built from the RSA,
或者更一般的讲，是基于陷门函数的
or more generally from trapdoors functions.
本讲我们看另一种公钥加密系统
In this lecture, we are going to look at public key encryption
这种是基于Diffie-Hellman协议的
schemes that are build from the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
那么首先回忆一下，一个公钥加密系统
So, first recall that a public key encryption system is
由三个算法组成。有一个
made up of three algorithms. There is a key
密钥生成算法，我记为Gen
generation algorithm that I will denote by Gen,
它会生成一个公钥
that basically generates a public key and a
和一个私钥，然后有两个算法
secret key. And then there are two algorithms: E
E和D，分别负责加密和解密。关键是
and D that encrypt and decrypt. And the point is
加密算法使用了公钥
the encryption algorithm encrypts using the
而解密算法使用了私钥进行解密
public key and the decryption algorithm decrypts
在物理世界中，公钥加密的类似物是
using the secret key. The physical world analogy for
一个保险箱
public key encryption is a locked box, where anyone
放一条信息在这个箱子里，然后给箱子上锁
can put a message inside the box and then lock the
这个锁就对应于公钥
box, that corresponds to the public key and then
然后没人可以打开这个箱子，除了有私钥的那个人
no one can open this box, except the person who has
也就是有钥匙的，可以把钥匙放进锁里
the secret key, that has the key can put it in the
解锁箱子，找回箱子里的信息
lock, unlock the box and the recover the message in
现在，上一讲里我们看了
the box. Now, in the previous lecture, we looked at
很多公钥加密的应用
a number of applications for public key encryption.
特别地，我们看了密钥交换的应用
In particular, we looked at the key exchange
事实上，这是公约加密
application, in fact, this is how public key encryption
在SSL中使用的方法，服务器发送它的公钥
is used in SSL, where the server sends its public
给浏览器，浏览器选择一个密钥
key to the browser, the browser chooses a secret
然后使用服务器的公钥把密钥加密
and then encrypts the secret using the server's
然后把解密结果发给服务器
public key, sends it back to the server, the
服务器解密，现在浏览器和服务器
server decrypts and now both the browser and the
就有了一个共享的密钥，他们可以使用这个密钥
server have a common secret that they can then
来加密双方互相通信的数据
use to encrypt data, going back and forth, between
那么在交互设定中，比如
them. So, in the interactive settings, such as in a
在网络协议中，公钥加密
networking protocol, public key encryption would
主要用来建立共享的对称密钥
primarily be used for setting up shared symmetric key
双方使用对称密钥来(安全)交换信息
which the two parties can then use to exchange
不过，还有很多情形是
information. However, there are many settings
交互是不可能的
where interaction is simply not possible and then
那么公钥加密直接用来加密信息
public key encryption is directly used to encrypt
一个例子是安全电子邮件
messages. One example of this is secure email.
某种意义上，这个电子邮件系统设计成非交互的
The email system in some sense is designed to be non-
这里发送方发送一封电子邮件
interactive, in the sense that the sender sends an
这封邮件会被接力转发
email, the email travels from relay to relay, to
直到到达目的地
relay, until it finally arrives at the destination
目的地应该能解密邮件
and the destination should be able to decrypt,
这里不需要与发送方互动
without interacting with the sender at that point.
这可以通过让发送方
That can be done basically, by the sender
使用接收方的公钥来加密信息实现
encrypting the message using the recipient's public
密文会沿着SMTP链传递
key. The ciphertext would travel along the SMTP chain
直到到达接收方
until it reaches the recipient. The recipient would
接收方会使用密钥解密并还原原先发送的信息
use a secret key and recover the original sent
不过，有很多的情况是
message. However, there are many other cases
交互是不可能的，我想给大家展示
where interaction is not possible and I want to show
两种这样的情况。第一个例子是
you two such cases. The first example is
文件系统。事实上公钥加密
file systems. And in fact, public key encryption is a
是一个很好的管理文件共享的方法，在一个加密的文件系统里
good way to manage file sharing, in an encrypted file
让我给大家展示这是什么意思
system. So, let me show you what I mean
那么设想这里，我们有我们的朋友Bob
by that. So, imagine we have our friend Bob
他想在某个存储服务器上存储一个加密的文件
here, who wants to store an encrypted file on some
那么他会写这个加密的文件
storage server. So, he will go ahead and write the
写到这个存储服务器上
encrypted file to the storage server. What he
Bob实际上向服务器写入了如下内容
actually writes in the server is basically the
他会生成一个随机文件加密密钥
following: he will generate a random file encryption key, we
我们称之为K_F，然后他会使用
will call it 'K sub F' and then he will use the
这个对称加密系统来加密文件
symmetric encryption system to encrypt the file
使用密钥K_F。然后他会解密这个密钥K_F
using the key 'K sub F'. Then, he will encrypt the
使用他自己的公钥
key 'K sub F', using his own public key. So public key
也就是Bob的公钥，这会让Bob可以在稍后的时间里访问这个文件
of Bob. This will give Bob access to the file at a later
使用他的私钥，Bob就可以解密这个头部
time, right. Using his secret key, Bob can decrypt
还原出K_F，然后他会
this header, recover 'K sub F'. Then he will
解密实际被加密的文件内容
decrypt the actual encrypted file and recover the
还原出文件的明文内容。那么，解密工作分两步
plaintext file. So, decryption will work in two steps.
不过，现在Bob想让Alice也有
However, Bob now wants also to give access to
访问该文件的权限
Alice, to this file. What he will do is, he will go
Bob会在这个头部里
ahead and in addition he will also include in the
放上使用Alice的公钥加密后的K_F
file header, an encyption of 'K sub F' under Alice's
好，那么注意这里没有任何交互
public key. OK. So, notice that there was no
Bob知道的只是Alice的公钥
interaction here. All that Bob knows is Alice's public
他可以让Alice稍后得以
key and yet he was able to the make the file
访问这个文件
accesible to Alice at a later time.
那么现在Bob消失了，然后Alice来了
So, now Bob disappears and then Alice
她要访问硬盘
comes and accesses the disk at a later time.
她会读这个密文，解密属于她的密文头部
She will read the ciphertext, decrypt her part of
还原K_F，然后她就能解密
the header, recover Kf and then she can decrypt
这个被对称加密的文件了
the symmetrically encrypted file and recover the
并还原实际的文件内容。好，那么大家可以看到
actual file contents. Ok, so you can see that without
没有任何交互，Bob就可以写这个文件系统
any interaction, Bob was able to write to the file
并让Alice也可以访问这个文件
system and enable Alice to access the file, as well.
同样的，在Alice读文件的时候
Again, at the time that Alice was reading the file, there is no
与Bob也没有交互，因为也许Bob联系不上了
interaction with Bob, because maybe Bob is already
但Alice依然可以读取文件的内容
inaccesible and yet Alice can still read the file
自己去解密还原
recovered by herself.
那么，另一个非交互的例子
So, another example of a non-interactive
公钥加密的应用是所谓的
application of public key encryption is what's called
密钥契约。现在密钥契约可能听起来
key escrow. Now, key escrow may actually sound
有点不好，但实际上在企业的工作环境里
like a bad thing but in fact it is a mandatory
(小圆告诉我们，契约确实不是什么好东西！)
这是一个强制性的特色。那么
feature in corporate environments. So, the idea
其想法是这样的。假设Bob向硬盘里写了数据
here is this. So imagine Bob writes data to a
稍后，Bob联系不上了
disk and then later Bob becomes inaccesible.
也许Bob被炒了，也许Bob病了
Maybe Bob is fired. Maybe Bob is out sick.
公司需要访问Bob的文件
And somehow the company needs to have access to
那么规定Bob是唯一
Bob's files. So having Bob be the only one
能够解密这些文件的人，在企业的环境里是行不通的
able to decrypt these files is simply unacceptable in
企业可能需要这些文件
corporate settings. The corporation might need
那么问题是该怎么办
access to those files. So, the question is what to do.
答案是引入这个实体
And the answer is to introduce this entity called
叫做密钥契约服务。这个系统工作的方式
a key escrow service. The way the system then
如下：
would work is as follows:
Bob在硬盘上的系统写他的文件
Basically, when Bob writes his file to disk, his
他把文件写到这个共享存储媒介上
system, as it's writing the file to this shared
与往常一样，它当然会
storage medium, what it would do of course, as before,
使用文件加密密钥K_f来加密文件
it would encrypt the file using the file encryption key Kf.
再用Bob的公钥加密K_f
It would encrypt Kf using Bob's public key, but it would
但是，它还会使用一个契约服务来加密K_f
also encrypt Kf using an escrow service. So here,
这里的契约服务完全是离线的
the escrow service is completely offline. We never
我们从不进行会话，除非我们需要服务
talk to it unless we actually need its services.
当Bob在写文件时，他只需要写
As Bob is writing the file, all he does is he simply writes
K_f的加密结果，使用契约方的公钥进行加密
the encryption of Kf under the escrow authority's
生成文件头部。现在
public key into the file header. Now, later Bob
Bob随后消失了，现在公司需要还原Bob的文件
disappears and now the company needs to recover
它会怎么做？在这里
Bob's file. What does it do? Well, at this point it would
它会联系契约服务。契约服务
contact the escrow service. The escrow service
会读这个文件头，使用它的私钥
would read this part of the header, use its secret
来解密文件头，以还原K_f，然后使用K_f
key to decrypt the header and recover Kf and then use Kf
来解密实际的文件
to decrypt the actual file.
好，这里大家注意，契约服务是
Ok. So, in this way again you notice that the escrow service was
完全离线的。与契约范围之间没有任何交互
completely offline. There was no interaction with the
直到我们需要用到契约服务时
escrow service until the point at which the escrow
同时，你还可以看到
services were actually needed. And again, you can
这是一个非常清楚优雅的公钥加密的应用
see that this is a very clean and elegant application
那么，如我在上一讲中所说
of public key encryption. So, as I said in the
我们看了基于陷门函数的
previous lecture, we saw constructions for public
公钥加密机制
key encryption based on trapdoor functions.
特别地，我们看了RSA
In particular, we look at RSA. We looked at the
我们看了通用机制叫做ISO标准
generic construction we called ISO standard.
我们看了像OAEP+等等这样的机制
We looked at constructions like OAEP+ and so on and so forth.
本讲中，我们来看基于Diffie-Hellman协议的
In this lecture, we are going to look at public key
公钥加密机制
constructions from the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
这是另外一族公钥系统
This is another family of public key systems and
我要给大家看它们是怎样工作的
I am going to show you how they work. These public
这些公钥系统叫做ElGamal公钥加密系统
key systems are generally called ElGamal public key
Taher ElGamal实际上是
encryption schemes. Taher ElGamal was actually Marty
Marty Hellman的学生，他提出这个ElGamal加密系统
Hellman's student. He came up with this ElGamal
是作为他的博士毕业论文的一部分
encryption system as part of his PhD thesis.
事实上，由于历史原因
And, in fact, ElGamal encryption, for historical
ElGamal加密被用于一个邮件加密系统叫做GPG
reasons, is used in an email encryption system called GPG,
GNU隐私卫士。通常
the GNU Privacy Guard. As usual, when we
当我们构建公钥加密系统时，我们的目标是
construct public key encryption systems, our goal is
构建选择密文安全的系统
to build systems that have chosen ciphertext security,
使得它们对抗窃听
so that they are secure both against eavesdropping
和篡改攻击是安全的。那么在我给大家看ElGamal系统之前
and tampering attacks. So, before I show you the ElGamal
我们来简单回顾一下Diffie-Hellman协议
system let's do a very brief review of the Diffie-Hellman
那么在我这里的表述里
protocol. So, in my description here, I am going
要比我们上周看到的版本稍微抽象一点
to abstract a little bit from the version that we saw last
事实上，我要使用一个概念
week. In fact, I just going to use the concept
叫做有限循环群。事实上我们有一个任意的有限循环群
of a finite cyclic group. In fact, we have an arbitrary finite
例如，它可以是群Z_p^*
cyclic group, for example, it could be the group (Zp) star,
但它也可以是椭圆曲线的点群
but it could also be the points of an elliptic curve.
如我说过的，使用椭圆曲线上的Diffie-Hellman
And as I mentioned, there are some benefits to doing
有一些好处。不过为求简便
Diffie-Hellman over an elliptic curve. But, for simplicity,
我只用G来表示一个抽象的有限循环群
I am just going to refer to G as an abstract finite
但在大家脑子里
cyclic group, but in your heads you should be
应把G想象成群(Z_p)
thinking G is the group (Zp) and let's suppose
(伊卡酱认为这里与现代数学思维正好相反)
设这个循环群有阶n，n为某个整数
that the group has order n for some integer n.
现在我们固定选取这个群里的一个生成元g
Now, we are going to fix a generator g of this group
这意味着，如果你看
and all this means, is basically, if you look at the
g的各次幂，你会得到
successive powers of g, that basically you get
群G中的所有元素。大家注意
all the elements in the group G. You notice,
因为群的阶为n，我们知道
because the group has order n, we know that
g^n = 1。所以
g to the power of n is equal to 1. And, therefore
看g的大于n-1次幂没有意义
there is no reason to go beyond the n-1st power
g^n=1所以我们就回卷到头了
of g. g to the n is equal to 1 so that we just wrap around.
好，那么我们有了这个循环群G
Ok. So, we have this cyclic group G. We have this
我们有这个生成元，它的幂给出了G中的所有元素
generator whose powers gave us all the elements of
现在让我提醒大家
G, and now let me remind you how the Diffie-Hellman
Diffie-Hellman协议是如何工作的。Alice选择一个
protocol works. Basically, what Alice does is she chooses a
随机数a。她计算g^a并把它
random a. She computes g to the a and sends it
发送给Bob。Bob选择一个随机数b，我们来看谁还记得
over to Bob. Bob chooses a random b. Let's see who
Bob给Alice发送什么？
remembers. What does Bob send over to Alice?
那么Bob给Alice发送g^b
So, Bob sends over to Alice g to the b and of
当然我应该提醒大家g^a
course I should remind you that both g to the a and
和g^b都是群G里的元素。现在
g to the b are just elements in this group G. Now,
他们可以推导出共享密钥了，如果大家记得
they can derive the shared secret, If you remember,
共享密钥是g^ab，这里的这些等式
the shared secret is g to the ab, and these equalities
证实了双方可以计算出
here shows that both sides can actually compute
共享密钥，有了他们各自的值
the shared secret given the values at their disposal.
那么，比如说Alice有了B，她自己有a
So, Alice for example, has B and she has a, and
那么计算B的a次方，她就会得到共享密钥
so raising B to the power of a, gives her the shared
当然攻击者很可怜
secret. The attacker, of course, the poor attacker
他能看到A和B，他现在的目标当然是
he gets to see A and B and his goal is now,
攻击者还知道生成元g
of course, he also gets to see the generated g, and
他现在的目标是计算g^ab。但是我们说过
his goal now is to compute g to the ab. But, we said that
我们相信这是一个难题，有g，g^a
this is believed to be a hard problem. Given g, g to the a,
以及g^b，在类似于Z_p^*的群里，要求计算g^ab
and g to the b, in a group like Zp*, computing g to
是困难的。那么现在我们看
the ab is difficult. So, now let's see how to convert to
然后将Diffie-Hellman协议转换成一个实际的公钥系统
the Diffie-Hellman protocol into an actual public key
如我所说，Taher ElGamal有一个很聪明的点子
system. As I said, this was a brilliant idea due to
那么与之前一样，我们固定选取我们的循环群G
Taher ElGamal. So, as before, we are going to fix our
和G中的一个生成元
cyclic group G and a generator g inside of G.
现在，我在这里重新写下了Diffie-Hellman协议
Now, here I wrote the Diffie-Hellman protocol again,
不过现在我们假设这些步骤在时间上
except now we are going to assume that these guys
是分开进行的。这两步不一定同时发生
are separated in time. These two steps do not have
他们可以
to occur simultaneously; they could actually take place
发生于不同的时间。Diffie-Hellman协议的第一步是
at quite different times. The first step of the Diffie-Hellman
我们将讨论的密钥生成
protocol is what we are going to view as key
公钥是这里的A
generation. That is the public key is going to be
对应的私钥是a
this capital A and the secret key is simply going to
那么当然，大家注意
be the little a. So, you notice of course that
从公钥提取私钥
extracting the secret key from the public key,
即从A提取a
namely extracting the little a from capital A is a
是个离散对数问题。那么还原私钥
discrete log problem. So, that recovering a secret
实际上是困难的。好，现在我们有了公钥
key is actually difficult. Ok, now this gives us our public key.
那么稍后Bob想给Alice加密一条信息
So, now at a later time Bob wants to encrypt a
使用她的公钥加密
message to Alice, encrypted using her public key.
那么Bob如何加密呢？
So how does Bob encrypt? Well, what he is going to do is
他会计算他对Diffie-Hellman的贡献
he's going to compute his contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
也就是说，他发送g^b
protocol. Namely, he is going to send over g to the
当然他随机选择这里的b
little b. Of course, he is going to choose this little b
现在他要自己计算
at random and now he is going to compute by
这里的共享密钥。那么
himself the shared secret. So, he is going to
Bob自己计算g^ab，根据这个g^ab
compute by himself g to the ab. From this g to the ab
他可以推出一个对称密钥
he is going to derive a symmetric key for a
用于对称加密系统，然后他
symmetric encryption system and then he is going to
使用这个刚刚推出的对称密钥来加密信息m
encrypt the message m using this symmetric key
这是Bob所要发送的
that he just derived. And that is the pair he is going to
他要发送他的Diffie-Hellman贡献
send. So, he is going to send over his contribution
加上信息m的对称加密结果
to the Diffie-Hellman protocol plus the symmetric
信息m是Bob想发送给Alice的信息
encryption of the message m that he wants to send
好，那么大家可以看到
over to Alice. Ok, so you can see basically, we are
我们做的事情与Diffie-Hellman协议一模一样
doing the exact same thing as we would do in the Diffie-Hellman
除了在我们这里，Bob直接使用
protocol except now we, Bob directly immediately is using
Diffie-Hellman对称密钥去加密
his Diffie-Hellman secret to encrypt the message  that he
他想发送给Alice的信息
wants to send over to Alice.
现在Alice要解密什么？
Now, what does Alice do to decrypt?
她要计算Diffie-Hellman的密钥
Basically, she is going also to compute the
记得，现在
Diffie-Hellman secret. Remember, that now she just
Alice收到了Bob的Diffie-Hellman贡献
received Bob's contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
她有她的私钥a。那么
protocol and she has her secret key a. So, she can
她可以计算Diffie-Hellman密钥了
compute also the Diffie-Hellman secret, namely
即g^ab，根据g^abAlice可以推出
g to the ab, from which she is going to derive the
对称加密密钥k。那么
symmetric encryption key k. And then, she is going
她解密信息以还原明文
to decrypt the message to recover the actual
好，这是我们如何
plaintext. Ok, so that is the intuition for how we
把Diffie-Hellman协议转成公钥系统的直观想法
convert the Diffie-Hellman protocol into a public key
顺便一说，在它提出时
system. By the way, this was kind of an interesting
有一个有趣的发展
development at the time that it came out, partially
部分是因为，大家注意这是一个随机加密算法
because, you notice this is a randomized encryption scheme.
那么每次Bob加密一条信息
So, every time Bob encrypts a message, it is
他需要选择一个新的随机b
required that he choose a new random b and
然后使用这个新随机数b加密信息
encrypt the message using this new random b.
那么我们来看ElGamal系统的更多细节
So, let's see the ElGamal system, actually in more
现在我们把它视为
detail. So, now actually let's view it as an actual
一个公钥加密系统，即算法三元组Gen
public key encryption system. Namely, algorithm Gen,
E和D
algorithm E and algorithm D.
那么通常，我们固定我们的n阶有限循环群
So, as usual, we are going to fix our finite cyclic
我们需要的另一工具是
group of order n. Another ingredient that we are going
一个对称加密系统。那么
to need is a symmetric encryption system. So, I am
我把它记为E_s和D_s
going to refer to it as E sub s, and D sub s. These are the
它们是对称加密系统的加密和解密算法
encryption and decryption algorithms of a symmetric
这个对称加密系统提供了
encryption system that happens to provide
认证加密。这个系统的密钥空间
authenticated encryption. And, the key space for
记为K。那么我们还需要
this system is capital K. And, then we are also going
一个哈希函数，它把群里的很多元素配对
to need a hash function that maps pairs of elements
即把G^2中的许多元素
in the group, namely elements in G squared into
映射到密钥空间。现在，公钥加密系统
the key space. Now, here is how the public key
如下工作：那么我必须描述三个算法
encryption system works. So, I have to describe
生成公钥和私钥的算法
three algorithms. Algorithm that generates the
然后是加密和解密的算法
public key and the secret key, and then the  encryption
那么，密钥生成算法
and decryption algorithms. So, the key generation
如下工作：
algorithm works as follows: All we do is basically,
我们构建Alice的Diffie-Hellman协议的贡献
build up Alice's contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
我们选择一个G中的
protocol. What we are going to do is going to choose a
随机的生成元g，然后我们
random generator g in G and then we are going to
现在一个随机指数a。私钥将是a
choose a random exponent a. The secret key is
然后公钥将是
going to be a and then the public key is going to be
生成元g和Alice的Diffie-Hellman协议的贡献
the generator g and Alice's contribution to the
顺便说下其原因是
Diffie-Hellman protocol. The reason, by the way,
我们并不使用固定的生成元，因为
we don't use a fix generator, is because it
它允许我们使用一个更弱的假设
allows us to somewhat use a weaker assumption,
提升安全性。那么最好是
improving security. And, so it is actually better to
每次选取一个随机生成元
choose a random generator every time. It is easy
选择一个随机生成元足够容易了
enough to choose a random generator. All we do, is we
我们取开始时选取的生成元
take the generator that we started with and then we
然后计算它的某个幂，其幂次与n互质
raise it to some power that is relatively prime to n.
这会给我们另一个生成元
That will give us another generator. A random
群G的一个随机生成元。好，那么大家可以看到
generator of the group capital G. Ok. So, you can
公钥就是Alice的
see here that again the public key is simply Alice's
Diffie-Hellman协议贡献
contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol. And, the
私钥是她选择的随机数a。现在
secret key is the random a that she chose. Now, how
我们如何加密和解密呢？
do we encrypt and decrypt? Well, when Bob wants
当Bob想加密信息时，他要使用公钥
to encrypt the message, he is going to use the
记得，它由g和h组成
public key. Remember, it consists of g and h.
他想加密信息m
Here, he wants to encrypt a message m.
那么Bob会
So, here is what he is going to do. So, he is going
选择他的Diffie-Hellman协议贡献
to choose his contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
通常在Diffie-Hellman中，他会选择私钥b
So, this is the secret b that he would normally
现在Bob要
choose in Diffie-Hellman. And, now he is going to
计算g^b，即他的信息
compute g to the b, which is actually his message,
在Diffie-Hellman协议中要发送给Alice的信息
that gets send to Alice in the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
他要计算Diffie-Hellman密钥
He is going to compute the Diffie-Hellman secret,
即h^b，如果大家还记得，h=g^a
that's h to the b. If you remember, h was g to the a,
因此这里的值就是g^ab
therefore, this value here is really g to the ab.
这就是Diffie-Hellman密钥。这个g^ab
That's the Diffie-Hellman secret. That is the one thing that
是攻击者所不知道的。接下来
the attacker doesn't actually know. Next, he is going
他要计算一个对称密钥
to compute a symmetric key by basically hashing
通过求二元组(u,v)的哈希值。那么当然
this pair u comma v. So, u, of course, is something
u是攻击者将会知道的东西，因为
that the attacker is going to know because that is
u将作为密文的一部分被发送
going to be sent as part of the ciphertext. But v, the
但是攻击者不会知道v。为了证明其安全性
attacker isn't going to know. Again, for the proof of
哈希u和v会有帮助
security, actually it helps to hash both u and v. So, we
那么我们计算两者的哈希，虽然严格说来
hash both of them together. Although, strictly speaking
我们只需要哈希v，因为v是唯一的
we just needed to hash v, because v is the only value
攻击者不知道的内容
that the attacker doesn't know. The attacker
攻击者已经知道了u，因为u是在网络上
already knows u, because that's going to be part of the data
发送的数据的一部分。那么Bob推导出
that's sent on the network. So, anyhow, so Bob derives
这个对称密钥k，通过计算u和v的哈希。然后
this symmetric key k, by hashing u and v. Then, he
Bob使用对称密钥k加密信息
goes ahead and encrypts the message using the
最后，Bob输出
symmetric key k and finally he outputs his
他的Diffie-Hellman协议贡献
contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
值u，然后是对称加密的密文
The value u and then the symmetric ciphertext that
是直接加密信息m后的密文
directly encrypts the message m.
完事。那么密文由两部分组成
That's it. So, the ciphertext consists of these two
这是在网络上发送的内容
parts and that is the thing that gets sent over the
我们看Alice是如何解密的
network. Let's see, how does Alice decrypt now.
那么她要使用她的私钥来解密
So, she is going to use her secret key a to decrypt
这里她接收了Bob的Diffie-Hellman协议的贡献
and she receives here, Bob's contribution to the
还有对称加密后的
Diffie-Hellman protocol plus the symmetric
Bob发送的信息的密文
encryption of the message that Bob sent.
她会自己计算Diffie-Hellman密钥
What she will do is she'll compute herself the Diffie-Hellman
如果大家记得，u^a就是(g^b)^a
secret. If you remember, u to the a is simply g to the b
即g^ab。那么这里
to the a. Which is g to the ab. So, here Alice
Alice计算了Diffie-Hellman密钥，现在我问大家
computed the Diffie-Hellman secret. And, now let me
她怎么推导出对称密钥k
ask you, how does she derive the symmetric key k
根据Diffie-Hellman密钥g^ab
given the Diffie-Hellman secret, g to the ab and the
以及她收到的密文呢？
ciphertext that she was given?
那么现在Alice
Well, what she will do, is simply again, now she has
从密文里获得了u，也有了v
u from the ciphertext and she has v, because she just
因为她自己能算出来。那么现在Alice可以重新推出
computed it herself. So, now she can rederive the
对称加密密钥，通过计算(u,v)的哈希
symmetric encryption key by hashing u and v
以获得对称加密密钥
together to get the symmetric encryption key and
然后她解密密文
then she just decrypts the ciphertext to get the
以获得实际的明文。好，完事了，这就是整个
actual plaintext. OK, so that's it. That is the whole
加密和解密算法。用图表示的话
encryption and decryption algorithm. In a picture,
密文看起来
the way the ciphertext would look, is also
与上一讲里我们看到的类似
as kind of what we saw in the last lecture. Basically,
包含u的会是个较短的报文头
there would be a short header that contains u.
大家回忆一下，它就是g^b，然后剩下的密文
Which as you recall, is g to the b. And, then the rest of the
将是待发送信息的加密结果
ciphertext would be the encryption of the message
使用对称密钥k加密
that is being sent, under the symmetric key k.
然后为了解密，Alice会使用这个报文头
And, then to decrypt, Alice would use this header
来推导Diffie-Hellman密钥
to derive the Diffie-Hellman secret from which she
继而推出密钥k，然后去解密报文内容
will derive k and then decrypts the body, to get the
以获得最初的明文。顺便说下，我应该提到
original plaintext. By the way, I should note that
我这里描述这个系统的方式，并非
the way I describe this system here, is actually not
ElGamal最初给出的描述
how ElGamal described it originally, this is
这是某种现代的观点来看ElGamal加密
in some sense a modern view about the ElGamal
但它与ElGamal的看法基本上是等价的
encryption, but it is pretty much equivalent to how
那么现在我们看
ElGamal viewed it. So, now let's look at the
ElGamal的性能。那么这里我写了
performance of ElGamal. So, here what I wrote
ElGamal加密中要花大量时间的步骤
is the, kind of the time intensive steps of ElGamal
即在加密中
encryption. Namely, during encryption, there are
有两步群G的指数计算
these two exponentiations in the group G.
指数是一个立方时间算法
Exponentiation, remember is a cubic time algorithm
使用重复平方算法
using the repeated squaring algorithm. And, as a
因此它是很花时间的
result, it is fairly time intensive. When I say, time
我说很花时间的意思是，在一个现代处理器上
intensive, I mean, that on a modern processor it would
它需要花掉几毫秒来计算指数
take a few milliseconds to compute these
而在解密时
exponentiations and during decryption, basically,
解密者要计算一个指数
the decryptor computes one exponentiation,
即u^a，这是解密的性能瓶颈
namely, u to the a. This is the bottleneck during
好，那么大家会认为
decryption. Ok, so you would think that encryption
加密的耗时是解密的两倍
actually is, takes twice as long as decryption, because
因为加密需要两个指数计算
encryption requires two exponentiations, while
而解密只需要一个。实际上
decryption requires only one. It turns out, that
这样说不完全准确，因为大家注意
is not entirely accurate because, you notice that the exponentiation
解密的指数计算里，底数可变
during decryption is done to a variable basis.
即每次的u都不一样
Namely, u changes every time. Whereas during
而在加密时，底数是固定的：g和h
encryption, the basis is fixed: g and h are derived
是由公钥推出的，是永远固定的
from the public key and are fixed forever.
那么事实上如果你想计算
So, in fact, in turns out that if you want to do
固定底数的指数，你可以做许多
exponentiation to a fixed basis, you can do a lot of
预备计算，特别地，你可以离线地
precomputation. In particular, you can do all the
把重复平方算法中的平方步骤的结果先算出来
squaring steps in the repeated squaring algorithm
那么这里你可以
offline. So, here what you would do, you would
先算出所有g的平方指数
compute all powers of 2 of g. So, you would
可以计算g, g^2, g^4
compute g, g squared, g to the fourth, g to the
g^8, g^16, g^32，等等。。
eighth, go to the sixteenth, g to the thirty two, and so
这些都是重复平方算法中
on and so forth. These are all the squaring steps of
所有平方步骤的结果，它们的计算可以离线完成
the repeated squaring algorithm you would do offline.
对h也可做同样的事情。那么
The same thing for h. And, then when it comes time to
在计算实际指数的时候，你只需要
actually do the real exponentiation all you need to do is just do the
计算余下的乘法了，把这些平方指数
multiplications, to accumulate these powers of 2 into the
根据指数b，来试图去计算
exponent b, that you're trying to compute.
那么如果大家想一想，这确实加速了
So, if you think about it, this can actually speed up
指数计算，速度是之前的3倍。事实上
exponentiation by a factor of 3. In fact, it would
它会加速更多，如果允许存储
speed up it even more if you allow me to store even
更大的表。这叫做窗口化的指数计算
larger tables. This is called a windowed exponentiation.
不过，如果允许加密者
But, regardless, if you allow the encryptor to
存储更大的由公钥推出的表
store large tables that are derived from the public
那么事实上加密就不会
key, then in fact encryption is not going to be
比解密慢了。事实上，加密快于解密
slower than decryption. In fact, encryption will be
但是这要求
faster than decryption. But, again, this requires that
加密者要预先计算这些大表
the encryptor to precompute these large tables
并存储它们。那么如果所有的加密者都这么做
and store them around. So, if all the encryptor is
只是加密单个接收方
doing, is just constantly encrypting to a single
这可以被很快地完成
recipient, that can be done actually fairly fast using these
使用这些预计算的表。如果加密者
precomputed tables. If the encryptor, for every
对每个信息都要加密给不同的接收方
message is encrypting to a different recipient, for
例如，如果每次发送电子邮件
example, if every time you send an email, you send
你要把邮件发送给不同的接收方，那么事实上
an email to a different recipient, then, in fact, the
解密要比解密慢一倍
encryption will be twice as slow as decryption.
那么这是一个值得记住的好技巧。事实上
So, this is a good trick to keep in mind. In fact, most
大多数的密码学库不是这么做的。那么如果大家看到
cryptolibraries don't do this. So, if you see that you
你总是用同一个公钥加密
are always encrypting to the same public key and
出于某些原因，你的加密过程需要很多时间
for some reason your encryption process takes a
对你来说是个瓶颈，请记得
lot of time, it's a bottleneck for you, keep in mind
你是可以加速的
that you can actually really speed things up
使用预先计算
using precomputation.
当然，如果加密对大家来说是个瓶颈
Of couse, if encryption is a bottleneck for you, you
大家也可以使用RSA，RSA的加密
might as well be using RSA, where an RSA encryption
还是非常快的。好，我们对ElGamal加密的
is really fast. Ok, so that is the end of our
讨论先到这里。现在，当然
description of ElGamal encryption. Now, the next
接下来的问题是，为什么这个系统是安全的？
question of course, is why is the system secure,
特别地，我们能否证明它是选择密文安全的？
in particular, can we prove that it's chosen
更重要地，基于什么样的假设
ciphertext secure and more importantly, under what
我们可以证明这个系统是选择密文安全的？
assumptions can we prove that the system is
那么我们
chosen ciphertext secure? So, we are going to
下节讨论之
discuss that in the next segment.